A Guide to the John K. Pickens Papers, 1964-1976
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
John K. Pickens Papers 1964-1976
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
57
4 boxes, 57A-57D (1.6 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Colonel Bernard Brenman, July 1981.
Alternative Form Available
Alexandria Archaeology has photocopies of this collection.
Biographical/Historical Information
John K. Pickens, Alexandria lawyer and city councilman, was instrumental in beginning formal archaeological studies in Alexandria. The studies began in the mid-1960s, under Richard (Dick) Muzzrole of the Smithsonian Institution. In 1975, the Alexandria Archaeology Commission (the AAC) was formed with John Pickens as chairman. Following Muzzrole's resignation as City Archaeologist in December 1975, the AAC began a search for his replacement.
Scope and Content
The collection contains organizational records of the Alexandria Archaeological Commission as well as correspondence with the Smithsonian Institution prior to the 1975 formation of the Alexandria Archaeological Commission. Clippings, research notes and archaeology notes are included as well. Topics include: formation of the Alexandria Archaeology Commission, archaeological digs along King Street, research on the Henry Piercy family, and area merchants.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into the following series:
Series I: Organizational Records (1964-1976) - Chronological by year
Series II: Clippings (1958-1976) - Chronological by year
Series III: Archaeology notes - Alphabetical by topic
Series IV: Research - Alphabetical by topic
Series V: Subject File - Alphabetical by topic
Series VI: Correspondence - Alphabetical by writer and then chronologically within each
Series VII: Printed Matter - Chronological by year
Series VIII: Miscellaneous
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Voges, Nettie Allen. Alexandria Digs up its Past, Part 4. Old Alexandria: Where America's Past is Present, McLean, VA: EPM Publications, 1975.
Related Material
Restricted subseries of correspondence.
Separated Material
Twenty-one (21) photoprints transferred to the photograph collection. Two (2) clay artifacts transferred to Alexandria Archaeology.
Index Terms
Alexandria Archaeology; Archaeology - Virginia - Alexandria; Muzzrole, Richard; Piercy family
Contents List
- Organizational Records, 1964-1976 (Box-folder 57A:1-10)
  - Organizational Records, 1964-1974. (Box-folder 57A:1)
  - Organizational Records, 1971. (Box-folder 57A:2)
  - Organizational Records, 1974. (Box-folder 57A:3)
  - Organizational Records, 1975. (Box-folder 57A:4)
  - Organizational Records, 1975. (Box-folder 57A:5)
  - Organizational Records, 1976. (Box-folder 57A:6)
  - Organizational Records - Committee of One Hundred, 1972. (Box-folder 57A:7)
  - Organizational Records - Committee of One Hundred, 1973. (Box-folder 57A:8)
  - Organizational Records - Council of Virginia Archaeology, 1975 and undated. (Box-folder 57A:9)
  - Organizational Records - Council of Virginia Archaeology, 1976. (Box-folder 57A:10)
- Clippings, 1958-1976 (Box-folder 57A:11-26)
  - Clippings - Gaithersburg Gazette, June 3, 1965. (Box-folder 57A:11)
  - Clippings, 1966. (Box-folder 57A:12)
  - Clippings, 1967. (Box-folder 57A:13)
  - Clippings, 1968. (Box-folder 57A:14)
  - Clippings, 1969. (Box-folder 57A:15)
  - Clippings, 1970. (Box-folder 57A:16)
  - Clippings, 1971. (Box-folder 57A:17)
  - Clippings, 1972. (Box-folder 57A:18)
  - Clippings, 1973. (Box-folder 57A:19)
  - Clippings, 1974. (Box-folder 57A:20)
  - Clippings, 1975. (Box-folder 57A:21)
  - Clippings, 1976. (Box-folder 57A:22)
  - Clippings - The Virginia Gazette, Visitor's Guide to Williamsburg, 1976. (Box-folder 57A:23)
  - Clippings - Richard Muzzrole, 1958-1976. (Box-folder 57A:24)
  - Clippings - John K. Pickens, 1976. (Box-folder 57A:25)
  - Clippings, undated. (Box-folder 57A:26)
- Archaeology Notes, 1971-1976 (Box 57B)
  - Archaeology Notes - Carlyle House, 1973-1976. (Box-folder 57B:1)
  - Archaeology Notes - Fairfax Street. (Box-folder 57B:2)
  - Archaeology Notes - 300 Block King Street, 1971-1974. (Box-folder 57B:3)
  - Archaeology Notes - 300 Block King Street, Preliminary Working Drawings, 1971-1972. (Box-folder 57B:4)
  - Archaeology Notes - 400 Block King Street, 1975. (Box-folder 57B:5)
  - Archaeology Notes - 300 and 400 Blocks King Street, 1974. (Box-folder 57B:6)
- Research (Box-folder 57B:7-13; 57C:1-7)
  - Research - Notes and Papers on Apprenticeships. (Box-folder 57B:7)
  - Research - Notes and Papers on Fires. (Box-folder 57B:8)
  - Research - Notes on Merchants, 1800-1850. (Box-folder 57B:9)
  - Research - Notes on Merchants. (Box-folder 57B:10)
  - Research - Notes on Merchants. (Box-folder 57B:11)
  - Research - Notes on Pages from Early (1806) Merchant's Ledger. (Box-folder 57B:12)
  - Research - Notes on Old Dominion Glass Works. (Box-folder 57B:13)
  - Research - Notes on Piercy and Potters. (Box-folder 57C:1)
  - Research - Correspondence on Piercy. (Box-folder 57C:2)
  - Research - Notes and Correspondence on Christian Piercy. (Box-folder 57C:3)
  - Research - Papers on Henry Piercy, 1976. (Box-folder 57C:4)
  - Research - Notes on Piercy family. (Box-folder 57C:5)
  - Research - Notes on Piercy family. (Box-folder 57C:6)
  - Research - Notes on paper, the press, and printing in Alexandria. (Box-folder 57C:7)
- Subject File (Box-folder 57C:8-22; 57D:1-13)
  - Subject File - Alexandria Gazette. (Box-folder 57C:8)
  - Subject File - Alexandria map, negative copy. (Box-folder 57C:9)
  - Subject File - 100 Block North Alfred Street, 1973. (Box-folder 57C:10)
  - Subject File - Annexation of a Portion of Arlington County...in 1915. (Box-folder 57C:11)
  - Subject File - Archaeology, Canal and Lyceum, 1969, 1974. (Box-folder 57C:12)
  - Subject File - Richard Arell and Arell's Tavern. (Box-folder 57C:13)
  - Subject File - Art and Antiques Newsletter by Bettie Wysor, Town and Country, 1972. (Box-folder 57C:14)
  - Subject File - Assurance Forms, Royal, King, Fairfax, Prince Streets, 1797-1827. (Box-folder 57C:15)
  - Subject File - Banking in Alexandria. (Box-folder 57C:16)
  - Subject File - Cabinet Makers, 1972. (Box-folder 57C:17)
  - Subject File - The City of Alexandria--One Time Capital of Virginia, by Robert Nelson Anderson. (Box-folder 57C:18)
  - Subject File - Deed Books. (Box-folder 57C:19)
  - Subject File - Disposition Maps. (Box-folder 57C:20)
  - Subject File - Early New England Pottery by Laura Woodside Watkins, 1966. (Box-folder 57C:21)
  - Subject File - Gadsby's Tavern, 1975-1976. (Box-folder 57C:22)
  - Subject File - Gunston Hall, Docents' Study Papers. (Box-folder 57D:1)
  - Subject File - Gunston Hall, report by J. Everette Fauber, Jr., AIA. (Box-folder 57D:2)
  - Subject File - Gunston Hall, report by Grigg, Wood & Browne, AIA. (Box-folder 57D:3)
  - Subject File - Gunston Hall, report by Richard Muzzrole. (Box-folder 57D:4)
  - Subject File - Gunston hall, report by Alain C. Outlaw, 1973. (Box-folder 57D:5)
  - Subject File - Robert H. McNulty reports, 1970. (Box-folder 57D:6)
  - Subject File - Pearlware: forgotten milestone of English ceramic history by Ivor Noel-Hume, 1969. (Box-folder 57D:7)
  - Subject File - Potters. (Box-folder 57D:8)
  - Subject File - Privies and Wells. (Box-folder 57D:9)
  - Subject File - 112 South Royal Street. (Box-folder 57D:10)
  - Subject File - Sailing Ships. (Box-folder 57D:11)
  - Subject File - Sennewald Biography Material. (Box-folder 57D:12)
  - Subject File - Silversmiths. (Box-folder 57D:13)
- Correspondence (Box-folder 57D:14-15)
  - Correspondence - Ivor and Audrey Noel-Hume, 1962-1976. (Box-folder 57D:14)
  - Correspondence - Smithsonian Institution, 1965-1976. (Box-folder 57D:15)
- Printed Matter (Box-folder 57D:16-17)
  - Printed Matter - The Government of the District of Columbia, two issues of Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, 1938-1966. (Box-folder 57D:16)
  - Printed Matter - The Alexandrian Magazine, September 1976. (Box-folder 57D:17)
- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 57D:18)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 57D:18)